Register of the Aleksandr Moiseevich Nekrich Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Aleksandr Moiseevich Nekrich papers,
1940-1996
96051
Nekrich, A. M. (Aleksandr Moiseevich)
62 manuscript boxes (25.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, writings, notes, printed matter, and photocopies of Soviet, American and German government documents, relating to twentieth-century Soviet history and foreign relations, the Soviet Union during World War II, and Soviet historiography.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Accruals
Increments may have been received since this finding aid was prepared. Please check Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/ to find the full extent of the collection.
Biographical Note
1920 March 3 Born, Baku, USSR
1941 M.A. in History, Moscow State University, USSR
1942-1945 Military service in the Soviet Army
1949 Ph.D. in History, USSR Academy of Science, Institute of History, Moscow
1950-1956 Junior Scholar, USSR Academy of Science, Institute of History, Moscow
1956-1976 Senior Scholar, USSR Academy of Sciences, Institute of History (reorganized in 1968 as the Institute of World History), Moscow
1963 Post-doctoral degree in History, USSR Academy of Sciences, Institute of History, Moscow
1976 October Emigrated to the United States
1976-1987 Senior Research Fellow, Russian Research Center of Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass.
1977, 1980 Visiting Lecturer, Brandeis University, Waltham, Mass.
1980-1981 Visiting Professor, Tübingen University, Federal Republic of Germany
1981 Visiting Scholar, Australian National University, Canberra
1982-1986 Editor-in-Chief, Obozrenie Magazine (Paris)
1983 Fellow, Slavic Research Center, Hokkaido University, Sapporo, Japan
1993 September 2 Died, Cambridge, Mass.
Scope and Content Note
This collection consists of the papers of Professor Aleksandr Moiseevich Nekrich, and covers mainly the period after he emigrated to the United States in 1976. It includes correspondence, writings, printed matter, and photocopies of Soviet, American, and German government documents, relating to twentieth-century Soviet history and foreign relations, the Soviet Union during World War II, and Soviet historiography.
Born in Baku, Azerbaijan, Nekrich graduated from Moscow State University and earned a Ph.D. at Moscow's Institute of History of the Academy of Sciences, where he also received a post-doctoral degree. From 1956 until 1976, he held the title of senior scholar at the institute.
In 1965, he published his famous book June 22, 1941, an account of Stalin's pre-war record, which also got translated in the West. The official Soviet view was that he had been a steady military commander of great wisdom. Stalin's crimes had been revealed years before by Nikita S. Khrushchev, but Dr. Nekrich's documentation of Stalin's blunders and Soviet unpreparedness for the German invasion of 1941 struck a raw nerve in Moscow, and he was expelled from the Communist Party in 1967. His freedom to write and work was then curtailed by the academic establishment, which was subservient to the Party's ideology. Finally, in 1976, Dr. Nekrich was allowed to leave the Soviet Union; he emigrated to the United States, where he joined the Harvard faculty as a research fellow, attaining the rank of senior fellow in 1987.
After he left the Soviet Union, more of Dr. Nekrich's books appeared on both sides of the Atlantic. They include The Punished Peoples, on Stalin's banishment of whole nationalities; Dr. Nekrich himself witnessed deportations in the Crimea, and his book traced the fates of those ethnic groups. (See also the entry for Crimean Tatars in the SUBJECT FILE.) Later, with Michael Geller, he wrote Utopia in Power, a widely acclaimed history of the Soviet Union. Fluent in German, he also completed a study of Soviet-German relations between the wars (see "Pariahs, Partners, Predators: German-Soviet Relations, 1922-1941," in the speeches and writings file).
His papers are arranged into nine series.
The largest and most interesting series contains his speeches and writings, including holograph and typescript drafts of the books mentioned above.
Also of interest is the material related to his work as editor of the Obozrenie Magazine from 1982 to 1986. The series contains a full run of the magazine, which gives a general picture of life in the Soviet Union (each issue was devoted to a specific aspect of Soviet society).
The biographical file is noteworthy because it documents the difficulties Aleksandr Nekrich had in obtaining legal permanent residence in the United States, and helps us understand his personality, character, values, and beliefs. It also contains letters he wrote his family when serving of the Russian front during World War II, which complement his memoirs about the war found in Box 21 of the speeches and writings file.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
World War, 1939-1945--Soviet Union.; World War, 1939-1945.; Soviet Union--Foreign relations.; Soviet Union--Historiography.; Soviet Union.; Russia (Federation); Soviet Union--History.
Series Description
- Biographical File, 1943-1993. (Box 1-3)
  Contracts, correspondence, legal documents, letters to his family, curriculum vitae, stationery, visa forms, relating mostly to Nekrich's war experiences from 1943 to 1945 and to his emigration to the United States, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Correspondence, 1976-1993. (Box 4-11)
  Letters sent and received from individuals, organizations and universities, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
- Research Material, 1939-1993. (Box 12-17)
  Copies of documents from American, German and Russian archives, index cards, notes, numerical files, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Speeches and Writings, 1962-1996. (Box 18-42)
  Articles, books, lectures, interviews, movie script, outlines, reviews, summaries, arranged chronologically by title
- Obozreniie Magazine, 1982-1986. (Box 43)
  Clippings, correspondence, illustrations, working material, and issues of the magazine, of which Nekrich was editor from 1982 to 1986, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Grants, 1976-1992. (Box 44-45)
  Correspondence, outlines, projects, proposals, reports, summaries, arranged alphabetically by name of institution to which Nekrich applied for grants
- Subject File, 1940-1991. (Box 46-49)
  Clippings, conference and seminar programs, correspondence, essays, memoranda, reports, statements, arranged alphabetically by name of the institution to which Nekrich applied for grants
- Printed Matter, 1962-1993. (Box 50-61)
  Articles from different sources, relating to various issues of World War II, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Photogrpahs, n.d. (Box 62)
  33 prints depicting Nekrich and various documents
- Audio-Visual Material, n.d. (Box 62)
  Film strip, microfilm reels, and phonotape cassettes
Container List
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1943-1993 (Box 1)
  - Contracts with publishing houses, 1977-1993 (Folder 1: 1-2)
  - Curriculum vitae (Folder 1: 3)
  - Legal documents (Russian and American certificates, refugee travel document, Aliens passport from Austria) (Folder 1: 4-6)
  - Letters to his family from the Russian front, 1943-1945 (Folder 1: 7-8)
  - Letters to his family from the Russian front, 1943-1945 (Box-folder 2: 1-3)
  - Letters to his family from the Russian front, 1943-1945 (Box-folder 3: 1-2)
  - Stationery (Folder 3: 3)
  - Subject file - Emigration to the United States, 1976
    - General (Folder 3: 4)
    - Correspondence, mostly with the United States Immigration and Naturalization Service regarding obtaining lawful permanent residence in the United States, 1977-1978 (Folder 3: 5-6)
    - Sworn statement (Folder 3: 7)
  - Visa forms (Folder 3: 8)
  - Miscellaneous (Folder 3: 9)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1976-1993 (Box 4)
  - General
    - General
      - Undated (Folder 4: 1)
      - 1976 (Folder 4: 2)
      - 1977 (Folder 4: 3)
      - 1978 (Folder 4: 4)
      - 1979 (Folder 4: 5)
      - 1980 (Folder 4: 6)
      - 1981 (Folder 4: 7)
      - 1982-1984 (Folder 4: 8)
      - 1985-1986 (Folder 4: 9)
      - 1987-1988 (Folder 4: 10)
      - 1989 (Folder 4: 11)
      - 1990 (Folder 4: 12)
      - 1991 (Folder 4: 13)
      - 1992 (Folder 4: 14)
      - 1993 (Folder 4: 15)
    - Personal
      - Undated (Folder 4: 16)
      - 1976-1977 (Folder 4: 17)
      - 1978-1979 (Box-folder 5: 1)
      - 1980-1982 (Folder 5: 2)
      - 1983-1986 (Folder 5: 3)
      - 1987-1989 (Folder 5: 4)
      - 1990-1991 (Folder 5: 5)
      - 1992 (Folder 5: 6)
      - 1993 (Folder 5: 7)
  - Albin Michel, 1976-1977 (Folder 5: 8)
  - Allen & Unwin Inc., 1988 (Folder 5: 9)
  - Alperovich, M., 1976-1990 (Folder 5: 10)
  - American Historical Association, 1979-1980 (Folder 5: 11)
  - American Historical Review, 1991-1992 (Folder 5: 12)
  - Anke, 1976-1977 (Folder 5: 13)
  - Ascher, Mr. and Mrs., 1976-1993 (Folder 5: 14)
  - Australian National University, 1980-1986 (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - Basic Books, Inc., 1979 (Folder 6: 2)
  - Bernstam, Michael, 1978-1979 (Folder 6: 3)
  - Brockman, John, 1977-1988 (Folder 6: 4)
  - Bumer, Boris, 1981 (Folder 6: 5)
  - Buromekskii, I., 1991 (Folder 6: 6)
  - Calmann-Lévy (France), 1991-1992 (Folder 6: 7)
  - Chronika Press, 1977-1980 (Folder 6: 8)
  - Citizens' Committee for Immigration Reform, 1982 (Folder 6: 9)
  - Daugava Magazine, 1990 (Folder 6: 10)
  - Editions la Découverte, 1990 (Folder 6: 11)
  - Fedorov, G. B., 1976-1979 (Folder 6: 12)
  - Forner, Patricia, 1977-1979. (Folder 6: 13)
    Includes her article "Death of a Russian Soul"
  - François Maspero, 1979-1982 (Folder 6: 14)
  - Freeman, M. Z., 1980-1981 (Folder 6: 15)
  - Gateway Editions, Ltd., 1977 (Folder 6: 16)
  - Grinnell College, 1979 (Folder 6: 17)
  - Harper Collins Academic, 1991 (Folder 6: 18)
  - Harper & Row, 1988-1990 (Folder 6: 19)
  - Harvard University Printing Office, 1976 (Folder 6: 20)
  - Heer, Nancy W., 1978 (Folder 6: 21)
  - Hela, M., 1976-1990 (Folder 6: 22)
  - L'Histoire, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 7: 1)
  - Hokkaido Daigaku. Subaru Kenkyu Shisetsu (Hokkaido University. Slavic Institute), 1981 (Folder 7: 2)
  - Hoover Institution on War, Revolution and Peace, 1977-1978 (Richard Burress, Alexander Dallin, Milorad Drachkovitch, Richard Staar, Robert Wesson) (Folder 7: 3)
  - Indiana University Press, 1978 (Folder 7: 4)
  - Inquiry Magazine, 1979 (Folder 7: 5)
  - Institute for Advanced Study (Princeton, N.J.), 1979 (Folder 7: 6)
  - Israel Research Institute of Contemporary Society, 1980-1981 (Folder 7: 7)
  - Kontinent, 1980-1982 (Folder 7: 8)
  - Lang Highlights, 1991-1992 (Folder 7: 9)
  - Likhter, A. I., 1978-1989. (Folder 7: 10)
    Includes his manuscript "Libava City at the Beginning of the Century"
  - London School of Economics, 1976-1989 (Folder 7: 11)
  - Kennan Institute for Advanced Russian Studies, 1977-1979 (Folder 7: 12)
  - Macmillan London Ltd, 1976 (Folder 7: 13)
  - Markiz, Flora, 1982 (Folder 7: 14)
  - Matrenin Dvor, 1976-1978 (Folder 7: 15)
  - Micciche, Pasquale E. (Folder 7: 16)
  - Michigan State University, 1977-1979 (Folder 7: 17)
  - Midstream, 1978 (Folder 7: 18)
  - Moskovskii Komsomolets, 1990 (Folder 7: 19)
  - Moskovskii Rabochii, 1990 (Folder 7: 20)
  - Naukova Dumka, 1991 (Folder 7: 21)
  - Nekrich, M. I., 1977-1985 (Folder 7: 22)
  - Nekridge, Simmi, 1977-1978 (Folder 7: 23)
  - Nekritz, Richard and Leah, 1981-1984 (Folder 7: 24)
  - New York Review of Books, 1976-1990 (Folder 7: 25)
  - New York Times, 1977 (Folder 7: 26)
  - Northern Illinois University, 1979 (Folder 7: 27)
  - Nosik, Boris, 1977-1979 (Folder 7: 28)
  - Ohio State University, 1977-1978 (Folder 7: 29)
  - Overseas Publications Interchange Limited, 1978-1992 (Folder 7: 30)
  - La Pensée russe, 1981-1989 (Folder 7: 31)
  - Pikhoia, R. G., 1993 (Folder 7: 32)
  - Princeton University Press, 1991 (Box-folder 8: 1)
  - Rasizade, Alex, 1989-1991 (Folder 8: 2)
  - Rosenblatt, Roger, 1988-1989 (Folder 8: 3)
  - Roshal, Devora, 1985-1986 (Folder 8: 4)
  - Routledge, 1990-1991 (Folder 8: 5)
  - Routledge, Chapman and Hall, Inc., 1991 (Folder 8: 6)
  - Rudolph, Margarita, 1976-1979 (Folder 8: 7)
  - Rumer, Boris, 1980-1981 (Folder 8: 8)
  - Russian archives, 1989-1990 (Folder 8: 9)
  - Russian Research Center, 1976-1991 (Folder 8: 10)
  - Russian Review, 1979 (Folder 8: 11)
  - Russkaia Mysl, 1982-1990 (Folder 8: 12)
  - Schoken Books Inc., 1976 (Folder 8: 13)
  - Schweizerisches Ost-Institut, 1981 (Folder 8: 14)
  - Shomroni, Vera, 1976-1992 (Folder 8: 15)
  - Shulman, Marshal L., 1978 (Folder 8: 16)
  - Simon, Gerhard, 1981 (Folder 8: 17)
  - Simon and Schuster, 1976 (Folder 8: 18)
  - Slavic Review, 1980-1992 (Folder 8: 19)
  - Slezkin, Iuri, 1981-1983 (Folder 8: 20)
  - Slezkin, L. S., 1978-1988 (Folder 8: 21)
  - Smith Richardson Foundation, Inc., 1989 (Folder 8: 22)
  - Solzhenitsyn, Alexandr and Natalia, 1966-1993 (Folder 8: 23)
  - Souvenir Press Ltd., 1976 (Folder 8: 24)
  - Survey (A Journal of Soviet and East European Studies), 1977 (Folder 8: 25)
  - Svetlova, K., 1978-1979 (Folder 8: 26)
  - Svirski, Grigori, 1976-1977 (Folder 8: 27)
  - United States. Senate. Foreign Relations Committee, 1978 (Folder 8: 28)
  - University of Alabama in Birmingham, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 9: 1)
  - University of Chicago, 1978 (Folder 9: 2)
  - University of North Carolina, 1977 (Folder 9: 3)
  - Unwin Hyman, Inc., 1988-1990 (Folder 9: 4)
  - Verlag Ullstein GmbH, 1980-1986 (Folder 9: 5)
  - Viking Press, 1978 (Folder 9: 6)
  - W. W. Norton & Company Inc./Publishers, 1977-1979 (Folder 9: 7)
  - WERS (Independent Publishing House), 1987 (Folder 9: 8)
  - Wissenschaftskolleg zu Berlin (Institute for Advanced dy Berlin), 1987-1988 (Folder 9: 9)
  - Miscellaneous. (Box 10-11)
    Includes some business cards
- RESEARCH MATERIAL, 1939-1993 (Box 12)
  - General
    - General (Folder 12: 1)
    - Anglo-American - Soviet diplomacy, 1941-1942 (Folder 12: 2)
    - German-Soviet relations, 1939-1941 (Folder 12: 3)
  - Copies of archival documents
    - American Archives (Folder 12: 4)
    - German Archives (Folder 12: 5-7)
    - German Archives (Box-folder 13: 1-7)
    - Russian Archives (Box-folder 14: 1-9)
  - Notes and index cards (Box-folder 15: 1-7)
  - Notes and index cards (Box-folder 16: 1-7)
  - Numeral files annotated by A. Nekrich (Folder 16: 8)
  - Numeral files annotated by A. Nekrich (Box-folder 17: 1-3)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1962-1996 (Box 18)
  - Untitled, n.d. (Folder 18: 1-9)
  - "Amerika: Kakoi Ia ee uvidel," n.d. (Folder 18: 10)
    Typescript
  - "Declassifying the Soviet Past," lecture, Yale Center for International and Area Studies, n.d. (Folder 18: 11)
  - "Dva pakta s natsistskoi Germaniei I ikh posledstviia," n.d. (Folder 18: 12)
  - "The Dynamism of History," n.d. (Folder 18: 13)
    Typescripts (in English and Russian)
  - "Dynamism of the Past," n.d. (Folder 18: 14)
  - "The Education of a Historian," n.d. (Folder 18: 15)
  - "Gorbachev, M.," n.d.
    - Holographs (Folder 18: 16)
    - Holographs (Box-folder 19: 1)
    - Typescripts
      - English (Folder 19: 2-4)
      - Russian (Box-folder 20: 1-3)
  - "In Honor of Helsinki," n.d. (Folder 20: 4)
  - "Intelligentsiia I Perestroika," n.d. (Folder 20: 5)
  - Interview with F. I. Golikov, n.d. (Box-folder 21: 1)
  - "Limits of Glasnost," n.d. (Folder 21: 2)
  - Memoirs relating to World War II, n.d. (Folder 21: 3)
  - Miscellaneous interviews, n.d. (Folder 21: 4)
    Typescripts
  - Movie script, n.d. (Folder 21: 5)
  - "Nepriiatnoe probuzhdenie," n.d. (Folder 21: 6)
  - "Pamiati Eleny Gessen," n.d. (Folder 21: 7)
  - "Perestroika I sotsialnye interesy," n.d. (Folder 21: 8)
  - "Politika, obrashchennaia v budushchee," n.d. (Folder 21: 9)
  - "Po doroge k voine s Germaniei," n.d. (Folder 21: 10)
  - "Povorot v mirovoi istorii," n.d. (Folder 21: 11)
  - "Primorazhivaet," n.d. (Folder 21: 12)
  - "Proshloe krepko nas derzhit," n.d. (Folder 21: 13)
  - "Raionnyi uroven' I perestroika," n.d. (Folder 21: 14)
  - "Sakharov: Narod I vlast," n.d. (Folder 21: 15)
  - "Sdvig vpravo," n.d. (Folder 21: 16)
  - "Soiuzniki ili vragi?" n.d. (Folder 21: 17)
  - "Soviet Historiography after Stalin," n.d. (Folder 21: 18)
  - "Soviet Union and the Second World War," n.d. (Box-folder 22: 1)
  - "The Soviet Union in the Khrushchev Era," n.d. (Folder 22: 2)
    Holograph and typescript
  - "Sovietskiie istoriki I perestroika," n.d. (Folder 22: 3)
  - "Stalin and the Pact with Hitler," n.d. (Folder 22: 4)
    Printed copy
  - "Stalin I natsistskaia Germaniia," n.d. (Folder 22: 5)
    Typescript and printed copy. Includes copy of German-Soviet non-aggression pact
  - "Uchenyi I vlast," n.d. (Folder 22: 6)
  - "Voina, kotoruiu nel'zia vyigtat," n.d. (Folder 22: 7)
  - "Politika angliiskogo pravitel'stva na severo-zapade Evropy," Novaia I noveishaia istoriia, 1962. (Folder 22: 8)
  - 1941, 22 iiunia, 1965
    - General (Folder 22: 9)
    - Typescript of first edition (Folder 22: 10)
    - Typescript of first edition (Box-folder 23: 1)
    - Reviews (Folder 23: 2)
    - Transcripts of discussions
      - Institute of Marxism-Leninism, 1966 February 16 (Folder 23: 3-5)
      - Central Committee of the Soviet Communist Party, 1967 March 3 (Folder 23: 6)
    - Introduction to Czech translation, n.d. (Folder 23: 7)
    - Typescript of second edition, 1991
      - English (Folder 23: 8)
      - English (Box-folder 24: 1-2)
      - Russian (Folder 24: 3-4)
      - Russian (Box-folder 25: 1)
  - "L'auteur de 'L'armée rouge assassinée' décrit les conditions faites en U.R.S.S. à un intellectuel 'normal': Une interview d'Alexandre Nekritch," Le Monde, 1965 August 1. (Folder 25: 2)
  - "Politika Anglii v Evrope," 1970. (Folder 25: 3-5)
  - Interview with V. Saltykov, 1973 July 3. (Box-folder 26: 1)
  - The Punished Peoples, 1975
    - Acknowledgement (Folder 26: 2)
    - Typescripts
      - English (Folder 26: 3)
      - Russian (Folder 26: 4-5)
      - Russian (Box-folder 27: 1)
    - Reviews (Folder 27: 2-3)
    - Broadcast transcript, n.d. (Folder 27: 4)
    - Miscellaneous (Folder 27: 5)
  - "The Arrest and Trial of I. M. Maisky," Survey, 1976. (Folder 27: 6)
  - "The Military and Civilian Society in the Soviet Union," 1976
    - Research proposal (Folder 27: 7)
    - Outline of intended book (Folder 27: 8)
    - Typescript (Box-folder 28: 1-3)
  - "Ti års faglig karantene efter oppgior med Stalin," Kultur, 1976 July 23. (Folder 28: 4)
  - "Le témoignage de Nekrich," interview, L'Express, 1976 August. (Folder 28: 5)
  - Articles concerning I.M. Maiskii, 1973, 1976. (Folder 28: 6)
    Typescript and mimeograph
  - Discussion-interview with Leo Valiani, 1976 September 16. (Folder 28: 7)
  - "Stalin's Blind Eye," 1976 October 21. (Folder 28: 8)
  - "The Belgrade Conference: Academician Sakharov's Article and the Dubious Position of the New York Times," 1977. (Folder 28: 9)
  - Review of Aleksander Zinov'iev, Ziiaiushchie Vysoty, 1977. (Folder 28: 10)
  - "The Soviet German Treaty of August 1939," 1977 May 18. (Folder 28: 11)
  - "The Menshevistic Idealist Abram Deborin," Survey, 1977-1978. (Box-folder 29: 1)
    Typescript and printed copy
  - Review of Nikolai Tolstoi, "Zhertvy Ialty," 1978. (Folder 29: 2)
  - "The Sunset of the Stalin Era," 1978. (Folder 29: 3)
  - "USSR and the Second World War," Brandeis University, 1978. (Folder 29: 4)
  - "The Soviet Union: An Orientation Course," outline, Harvard University, 1978 August 20-25. (Folder 29: 5)
  - "The Impact of the Second World War," lecture, Science Center, 1978 August 21. (Folder 29: 6)
  - "They Couldn't Go Home Again," The Washington Post, 1978 November 12. (Folder 29: 7)
  - Otreshis ot strakha, 1979
    - Correspondence (Folder 29: 8)
    - Holograph (Folder 29: 9-10)
    - Holograph (Box-folder 30: 1-5)
    - Typescript of Russian edition (Folder 30: 6)
    - Typescript of Russian edition (Box-folder 31: 1-2)
    - Reviews (Folder 31: 3)
    - Summary (Folder 31: 4)
    - Typescript of English translation, Forsake Fear, 1991 (Folder 31: 5-6)
    - Miscellaneous (Folder 31: 7)
  - Review of Elena Karer, "Raspavshaiasia Sovetskaia Imperiia," 1979. (Box-folder 32: 1)
  - "Nazi-Soviet Non-Aggression Pact in Retrospect," speech, 1979 December 21. (Folder 32: 2)
  - "Pokhod protiv 'kosmopolitov' v MGU," 1980 December. (Folder 32: 3-7)
    Holograph and printed copy
  - "Voina," lecture, 1981 January 12. (Folder 32: 8)
  - "Uchenyi I vlast'," lecture, Norwegian Pen-Club, 1981 March 4. (Folder 32: 9)
  - "Ikke Hauker/duer I Kreml - Bare rene Marktpolitikere," Reportasjer, 1981 March 5. (Folder 32: 10)
  - "Stalin and the Pact with Hitler," Russia Magazine, 1981 April. (Folder 32: 11)
  - "Pered vtorzheniiem," Russkaia mysl, 1981 July 2. (Folder 32: 12)
  - "Chemu uchit istoriia," Novoe russkoe slovo, 1981 September 27. (Folder 32: 13)
  - Utopiia u vlasti (with Michael Geller), 1982 (Box 33)
    - Typescript of English translation, Utopia in Power, 1986 (Folder 33: 1-3)
    - Cover color proof (Folder 33: 4)
    - Reviews (Folder 33: 5)
    - Reviews (Box-folder 34: 1)
  - "Chemu uchit istoriia," interview, Novoe russkoe slovo, 1983 September 27. (Folder 34: 2)
  - "Modest Proposition," East and West Magazine, 1984 April. (Folder 34: 3)
  - "The German Question Today," 1985. (Folder 34: 4)
    Typescript of chapter contributed to unidentified book
  - "The Soviet Intelligentsia during the Khrushchev Era," 1985
    - Background material on the origin of the word 'intelligentsia' (Folder 34: 5)
    - Holographs (Folder 34: 6)
    - Typescripts
      - English (Folder 34: 7)
      - Russian (Folder 34: 8-9)
  - Interview with Iurii Liubimov, 1985 February 25. (Box-folder 35: 1)
  - Interview with Oleg Tselkov, 1985 February 28. (Folder 35: 2)
  - "Pochemu Gorbachev nervnichaet?" Russkaia zhisn, 1986 October 22. (Folder 35: 3)
  - "Armiia I grazhdanskoie obshchestvo," 1987. (Folder 35: 4)
  - "Perestroika," 1987. (Folder 35: 5)
  - "Tough Questions Still Unanswered," World Paper, 1987 November. (Folder 35: 6)
  - "The Political Struggle Surrounding Perestroika in the Soviet Union," 1988. (Folder 35: 7)
  - "Sushchestvovala li perepiska mezhdu Stalinom i Gitlerom?" Russkaia mysl, 1988 April 8. (Folder 35: 8)
  - "Urss: Verso una nuova dittatura?" Giornale di Brescia, 1988 September 17. (Folder 35: 9)
  - "Perestroika in History," Survey, 1988 October. (Folder 35: 10)
    Typescripts and printed copy
  - "Grigorenko: Voennyi intelligent-buntar," 1988 November. (Folder 35: 11)
  - "Sovetskaia sistema v svete chernobyl'skogo krizisa," 1988 November 8. (Folder 35: 12)
  - "Obshchestvo rastrachennoi energii," 1988 November 13. (Folder 35: 13)
  - "Nepredskazuemost' sovetskogo proshlogo," 1989 (?). (Folder 35: 14)
  - "Historia ja Perestroika," Moskovan uutiset, 1989. (Folder 35: 15)
  - "Moment istorii," Russkaia mysl, 1989 July 21. (Folder 35: 16)
  - "Istoriia: Tazheloie Remeslo," interview, Poisk, 1989 October. (Box-folder 36: 1)
  - "Na piatom godu perestroiki," 1989 October 1. (Folder 36: 2)
  - "SSSR, istoriia I perestroika: Vzgliad iz-za okeana," Moscow News, 1989 October 8. (Folder 36: 3)
  - "De la NEP à la perestroika," 1989 October 26. (Folder 36: 4)
  - "Two Nazi-Soviet Pacts and their Historical Consequences," 1989 November. (Folder 36: 5)
  - "Perestraivaia proshloie," lecture, 1989 November 30. (Folder 36: 6)
  - "Ia nashel svoe mesto," interview, Poisk, 1989 December. (Folder 36: 7)
  - Lecture on the Soviet-German Pact, Russian Historical Archival Institution, 1989 December 7. (Folder 36: 8)
  - "Istoriia i vlast," interview, Uchitel'skaia Gazeta, 1989 December 12. (Folder 36: 9)